The first homework question is about
strategy.
Like where is
Nagarjuna going, right?
He's made his famous
opening lines eight invisibles.
Then the next verse he gave you four
choices about where things come from.
So where is he going to go? And then he
gives you the different kinds of
causes. What's the connection by the way
between the second verse
and the third verse? The second verse
gives you four choices. Things come from
themselves, things come from something
else.
And then the fourth verse Buddha
suddenly jumps in
and presents four kinds of conditions.
What Why did
Buddha interrupt the show?
Yeah, good. Yeah, but
Buddha taught us four kinds of
conditions
to demonstrate how things come from
something else, okay?
So that's the connection between the two
verses, okay?
So often times be careful.
These Nagarjuna verses
many of the verses are false
because they are the other guy. So
people quote Nagarjuna and Nagarjuna
said, "Bubba, no, you forgot to read the
first
It says the other guy said
You see what I mean? It's very common.
People quote Nagarjuna to prove
something.
But it's actually Nagarjuna the wrong
guy.
Okay, so be careful. All right.
So really that third verse is kind of uh
the other guy
is presenting the four kinds of
conditions
that Lord Buddha taught. And he said
Lord Buddha said
things come from something else. He said
it four times, four different ways,
okay?
That's maybe why
they seem to overlap a little bit, like
number one and number four, condition
number one
and condition number four, they're the
same thing.
Uh just said it in a different way,
okay?
All right.
So I
Tony Lama
gives you a structure for the first
chapter. You By the way, I I know many
many people uh tried to translate this
book.
And just forget it.
It's It's ridiculous. It's not wrong,
it's
It's like uh I don't know, somebody very
drunk translating or something. It's all
wrong.
Uh
they don't understand that they He's He
has a plan.
He There's a reason what Like he quotes
the Buddha suddenly
uh with those four kinds of conditions.
There's a reason. He's trying to explain
the third verse, the last verse, okay?
So you have to see the structure. And
for that you need a
commentary. And there are great
commentaries. There are
for
for 1,000, 2,000 years, more than 2,000
years, okay?
All right, and we're going to talk about
some of them. All right.
Uh
Mong the Tong Ne
Masoom
Mong the Tong Ne Tok Tokpa
No. No, that's Tok
I'm talking Dogpa.
Uh Dogpa means uh that's Dogpa.
Uh Dogpa means I fear.
Uh my explanation would be get too long.
If I teach you all the other
commentaries,
uh talk monk to talk. Very famous excuse
in scripture.
Okay.
Not really.
So, I want to tell you a little bit
about the strategy
from the third verse to the end, okay?
He has a strategy.
And the reason I wrote a homework
question is cuz
Chönyi Lama explained it, but I I
couldn't figure it out. I was nervous
about getting the homework done, and I
couldn't think straight.
Uh so, I said, "Slow down, Geshe
Michael. Whenever you can't understand,
slow down."
I'm like, "Slow down." Figure out his
struct- He has a structure. He tells you
the structure. So, slow down and read
it. That's why he put it there.
Okay.
Uh so, he has five steps
for the rest of the chapter.
Okay.
And it's actually six
because number three has two parts.
Okay? So, here we go.
Step number one.
He quotes
the four kinds of conditions from
Buddha, okay?
He quotes the other guy
quoting the Buddha. This is the
structure for the chapter, okay? For the
rest of the chapter.
Uh if you don't have enough homework
questions,
go to the structure.
Okay.
Number two.
Uh
he puts all them
together.
Uh
he
and shows that they have no nature of
their own. And we're going to talk about
nature, I think, tomorrow. What's it
mean
to have a nature of your own? Okay?
He puts them all together
and he shows they don't have any nature.
Okay?
Number three.
Mhm.
He wants to discuss the process of the
sprout coming out.
Okay? So, the process,
the coming out of the sprout, in English
it's a
i-n-g word, gerund, the coming
of the sprout. Okay? He wants to see how
the sprout is
coming
from the seed. So, the emphasis, when
you say coming,
is not on the starting of the coming
and not on the ending of the coming.
It's on the middle of the coming. Okay?
And that's going to be important in the
next chapter,
where we discuss coming and going. Okay?
So, there's three parts
to a sprout that you can think about.
One is when it first pops out.
One is while it's growing.
And one is when the tree finished
growing, right? Then it starts to die,
right?
Okay? So,
when he's looking at the process
of growing, okay, that's the middle
part, right? The growing part, before
the tree is
10 ft higher, you know, while it's
growing. He wants to look at that.
And he looks at that in two parts. Okay,
this is 3a and 3B, right?
3A and 3B.
Uh
Number 3A.
What is the process of growing?
You know, which is
the tree is involved with, okay?
The tree
has some relationship
with the growing time, with the growing
time, not the finished time,
but during the growing time.
Something's happening between the tree
and the growing. He's going to look at
that. 3A, okay? 3B.
Uh
How does that middle period, while the
tree is growing, lead into the final
period? You see? So, it's kind of like
how does the growing
lead into the final tree? Okay? So, he's
going to concentrate on the end of the
growing
before
the end of the growing part, before the
grown part. Got it?
You okay? Everyone confused?
Took me like 2 hours.
Okay.
All right. Mm,
number four.
From the seed's point of view,
he's going to talk about
how does it first start the result? How
does it first start the growing? Okay?
So, he's going to the front front of the
growing time.
How does the
front of the growing time start? How
does the seed first crack open before
anything comes out?
You know, what what happens at that
moment, okay?
From the seed's point of view, why does
he Okay, for $50,
everybody wakes up.
Why does he say from the seed's point of
view?
Because
Uh I saved my money.
The first verse
talked about the results point of view,
right? What is the second verse?
Second verse.
The second verse
talked about things
from the results point of view, okay?
That we finished that already.
Now we're talking about results from the
seeds point of view, okay? Got it?
Okay. So from the seeds point of view
how does the thing start? Okay.
Okay.
And then
uh
we're on number five, right?
Uh this is cool. He says, "I'll show you
why each one of those four causes
aren't really causes." He goes through
them one by one.
Okay? So
one, two, three, four are all general
about all four.
Then he says, "Now let me show you why
each one is not real seed." And then he
talks about cause condition, and then he
talks about object condition, and then
he talks about just after it condition,
and then he talks about a
self-sufficient condition, okay?
So he's going to
wipe them out one by one. And that's
where your homework question ends.
There's also a dessert, okay? At the end
of the chapter. He goes back to the
four.
He does a cute little wrap-up.
It's not that different from the
beginning of the four, okay? You good?
All right.
Uh let's keep going.
Okay.
Um, homework question two.
Um.
I'll just read the question, okay?
All right.
With all four kinds of conditions
with all four, Ayya Indacanda has a
problem.
And he says, "I don't like it.
I have a problem
when you say
the tree is growing from the seed. It's
uncomfortable for me." There's a very
common expression in the monastery
when a teacher's teaching, they'll say,
"The The debarment tool."
They go like this with their hand. The
The debarment tool, you know, this This
author says that, but
I'm not so comfortable with it, okay?
Uh,
I have a problem when you say
the tree is growing from the seed, okay?
And then he goes to Mikan, he goes to
object factor, and he repeats it, okay?
Cuz the first
thing he said kind of relates more to
the first cause. I have a problem when
you say tree is growing from the seed.
Then he says, "I also have a problem
when you say
that the awareness of blue
is growing from your eye."
Okay? Your eye
just detect color and shape. It doesn't
think. The eye cannot think. The eye
just called a
called the mind. You see, "Hey, we got
something out here." "What?" "Hey, it's
kind of like, you know, sky. It's the
same as the sky." "Oh, you You it's
big?" "No, no, I'm talking about color.
Oh, it's blue. So that the mind makes
those decisions. The eye just cause the
mind says, we got something out here.
Okay, we got something out here. So he
says I have a problem with saying that
when you look at blue
uh you get
it it triggers an awareness in your
mind. Okay? I have a problem with saying
the awareness of blue comes from seeing
blue.
I have a problem with that. And I have a
problem with saying that the
tree
is growing from the seed. It's growing
cuz now we're focusing on the process,
okay? I have a trouble with that.
I have a problem when you say the tree
is growing from the seed. Or the
awareness of blue is growing from the
blue. I have a trouble with that. It's
It's
it's not so comfortable for me. I feel
uncomfortable when you talk like that.
Okay?
Then he quotes a very very thing in
Buddhism. Very famous thing in Buddhism,
okay?
And I just threw it in there to the
question.
Okay? It says it means when he says
okay, and what he's going to say next
is connected to the answer to the
question, okay? Ready? Very very famous
thing.
Ready? It's hard.
As the result
approaches growing
as the result
as the tree
approaches
growing
the seed approaches ending.
Okay? As the
tree
approaches
growing
the seed approaches ending.
And in fact those two must be
simultaneous.
They must be simultaneous. They must
happen at the same time. It's a little
bit
your question.
Uh you know, where where do they
overlap? Okay?
As the
result as the tree approaches growing,
the seed of the tree approaches
ending.
The ending of the seed
and the growing of the tree,
first growing of the tree, final ending
of the seed, must be simultaneous if
there's to be contact.
If there's no contact, then then,
you know,
apple seeds can make pigs.
Or anything. There's no contact. Okay,
got it?
You all right?
Okay.
Uh
So, two things are simultaneous.
The
as the result
as the tree approaches growing
and the seed is approaching ending,
right? Over time.
Like if it takes
2 weeks for the tree to
come out, those processes happen at the
same time. Okay? The process of the seed
ending
and the process of the tree coming out
are happening at the same time. Okay?
That over a 2 weeks or 3 weeks or 1
month. Okay? Got it?
And at the end of the process, at the
end of both process,
the growth of the result
and the completion of the stopping of
the cause happen at the same time. Okay?
The last moment of each
happens Sorry. The last moment of the
ending of the cause and the first mo-
moment of the finished tree happen at
the same time. Okay?
They Those two things happen at the same
time. Okay?
Okay.
These two things are happening at the
same time, and these two things are
happening at the same time.
These two things are single instance.
These two things are going on for a
couple weeks or something. Okay?
This one is the first one I mentioned.
The whole
ending of the seed, which takes time,
and the whole coming out of the tree,
which takes time,
those happen during the same period.
Okay?
And
the end of the processes
happen at the same time. When the seed
finally dies, the tree
has grown.
Then you have a tree. Then you have a
full tree. Okay? At that moment, you
have a real tree.
Okay? Got it?
Now, uh
Here's the homework answer.
Okay, just turn on your iPhone.
Uh
If we think carefully, and I always put
that at the front of the answer because
it means uh
You know, if you don't think carefully,
everything's fine.
The tree grew through from the seed,
Gishla. What's the problem? You know, I
don't have a problem. Melissa's baby is
growing from some seed.
It What's the problem? Okay, it's it's
normal. Don't get all freaked out.
You know, but if we think more
carefully,
we can see that it's not really correct
to say
the tree is growing up because during
the growing, there's no tree
yet.
It doesn't have leaves. It doesn't have
fruits. It doesn't have branches. How
can you say the tree is growing
when there's no tree yet?
Got it?
But I you know, we say the baby is
growing, but it's not a baby yet,
Michael.
You'll know
when it's a baby. They'll They'll be all
night in the hospital or
I went to Aura's birth. It was me and D.
And we stopped after 48 hours. We went
home.
Uh
But the It's not a You can't say the
baby is growing. It's not a baby yet.
It's a baby when it comes out. You see
what I mean? So, we all say the baby is
growing. We all say the tree is growing,
but it's wrong.
We all making some big mistake. Got it?
Okay? If it's true
that the end of the grow the cause
and uh
growing of the tree
take the same time period or happening
in
Because when you say the growing of a
tree, what you mean is it's not a tree
until it finished growing. It has fruits
and
and stuff, okay? You all right?
Okay.
Uh
We cannot be seeing what we think we
see.
And the tree must actually be coming
from a different place than the seed.
Okay? The book must be coming from a
different place than the pen.
Okay? It looks like the book comes from
the pen. It looks like the movie comes
from a Hollywood studio.
But really, it's coming from your seats,
okay? It's coming from your seats.
What you think you see,
the tree is growing from the seed, is
impossible. Not possible. There is no
tree.
Okay? And once there's a tree, there's
no
seed.
What do you mean the tree is growing
from the seed? They didn't happen.
There's no overlap at all.
Okay? by the time you have a tree,
there's no seed.
While you have a seed, there's no tree.
How can you say the seed is going for
the tree? What's wrong with you?
Oh, Geshe la, I'm writing it on my
homework.
Are you?
Then, you know, the natural thing is, so
Geshe la, I mean, by the way, when you
talk to your friends about this stuff,
they're like, "Oh, that's very
interesting."
Okay.
If you don't If someone offers to cook
you something, which he always does, and
you should take it.
Uh, they say, "You want me You want to
try this new dish?" I'm like, "Yeah."
This new Sicilian dish, right? And I'm
like, "Yeah, I want to taste that." And
then he afterwards he says, "How'd you
like it, Geshe la?" And you say,
"That was interesting."
What? What's the question interesting?
You can get to the same
conclusion by using the idea of of
moments of time.
Yeah, there's
I'm saying like
if the tree's going to arrive in in a
second from now, and then dividing it
into a half a second, and so on and so
forth. It just seems a lot cleaner in my
mind.
So
Uh, there's 27 ways to do it.
And
and
the reason there's 27 is that different
ones are attractive to different
students.
So, you if you're lower Hinayana, you
just take one and you say, "That's more
attractive. I don't need the others."
If you're a Bodhisattva, you say, "Teach
me the 27
cuz maybe I can help weird people."
Okay, like number 26 fits like three
people in the world.
Teach it to me. I might be on a plane
with them someday.
You know, okay? Yeah, perfect.
Perfect. In fact, it's going to be hard
for me to keep them separate. Uh that's
part of my job.
I shouldn't tell you the chapter on time
while I'm teaching you the chapter on
conditions, but it's hard.
The temptation is very strong to go
there.
Okay. All right.
Uh
next homework question.
You guys okay? I'll give you a pee pee
break after a juice break after this
one. Okay. Deal?
Deal. Okay.
Uh
the growing of the understanding and the
ending of the class
happened
Uh
So, that was talking about the process
of growing. That was talking about the
process of growing, right?
And uh now we're talking about
how it leads into the result, right?
We're talking about I forget what number
it was, but
how it leads into the result at the end
of the growing
before you hit the result.
How does it How does the process lead
into the result? Okay.
Here's the question on the homework.
Someone responds to this train of
thought by saying, "Why talk so much,
Aryadeva?
We know that when we see an apple
there must be an eyeball working as a
cause which helps create the perception
of the apple. If I see an apple, it
proves I have a
eyeball.
eyeball. Okay.
Then uh when you see the result
you know the cause must have been
causing the result to grow.
That's all. Why blah blah? Stop blah
blah.
For some reason I think they blame this
on the citrus school. Now, maybe Nick
can give us a report tomorrow. I don't
know.
Anyway,
uh I don't know why. Uh
You ready?
The gardeness says
What she say?
You can't talk about a thing growing
until it's finished.
Okay? Like it's
You can't say the tree is growing
or the baby is growing
before the baby comes before the baby's
a baby.
You see what I mean? Got it?
It's it's weird
to talk about the tree growing. By the
way, what if the
What if there's no water and the thing
dies? Will you say the tree died?
Will you say the tree died
before the tree came
grew?
You can't say the tree died. There was
no tree yet.
You can say the the future tree dying
or the tree that was you know, the thing
that was going to become a tree. That's
okay. Maybe that's okay.
Died. You can say that, but but it
really is wrong to say the tree died
before the tree grew.
Okay? Got it? After it grew it can die.
That's what happens to trees in Arizona.
Okay. All right. I remember when I went
to Princeton, it wasn't the school that
impressed me, it was the trees.
Uh
okay.
Okay.
That is we can say a tree is growing.
The reason we say a tree is growing
what we really mean is at the end of the
growing, there's a tree.
Okay? When we say this the translators
must have a headache. I don't know.
You doing okay?
You're amazing. We should give them a
hand again. Yeah.
Wow.
Okay, when we say I'll repeat for me and
for you.
When we say a tree is growing, we can
say that
because at the end of the process,
there's a finished tree.
Uh okay.
You should only be able to say
a tree is growing
after the growing.
I'll say it again.
Yeah, I know.
You should only be able to say
a tree is growing
after it finished growing cuz there's no
tree yet before that.
Okay? This By the way, I mean, I don't
know if he's going to go into it.
There's something wrong with human
language.
language. The word me
and you
is already a mistake.
Every language has tenses, conjugations,
plural, singular, it's all wrong.
People say God never talks. I said,
"Yeah, you cuz you can't understand
None of his vocabulary is in your
vocabulary."
You know, I never heard Vaniyogini talk
to me.
They don't know how to talk to you.
Tree grows? What do you mean?
What do you mean tree grows? They're
like
You can't say that.
Okay?
Anyway,
uh
maybe the reason they don't talk to us
more is that our languages are so
completely different, you know. Okay.
Uh with a
now
it's not so bad
with a direct cause, okay? Don't forget
there's two kind of causes
traditionally, direct cause and indirect
cause. If you're not sure about it, ask
Adam.
He spent like six months on it.
We were all so fed up with direct causes
and indirect causes. We were like,
"What's the next subject?" We were going
to skip a couple pages translation and
see if anybody noticed.
Uh
Okay.
Direct cause, seed.
Uh indirect cause, the guy who came and
planted the seed.
Okay? Direct cause,
the seed.
Okay? Indirect cause, the guy, you know,
I don't know, couple weeks before
who came and planted the seed. Okay?
Is now a question.
If you say geshla, if you you know, if
you say in the garden, you know,
give me a break.
You know?
We can say the tree's growing. It's
technically is not correct.
Okay? We can say the tree is growing
from the tree seed. Okay?
Don't don't hassle us.
Okay, technically
there's no tree until the end.
So, we understand that, but
you know, somebody has to water the tree
even though there's no tree.
Got it? So, we just say stuff like that.
We know it's not exact,
but otherwise, who's going to water the
tree, you know?
You wouldn't say, "Can you go out and
water the potential?"
You know?
They're like, "What?"
It's hard enough to hire people at
Diamond Mountain.
Can you go out water the potential? You
know?
So, give us a break, you know. It's
going to be here soon.
You know, there's a stick coming up.
It's going to have leaves
very soon.
We can talk about a tree
growing. Then the garden says, "No, you
can't."
What about indirect causes? You going to
say the guy planted a tree? Is that what
you're going to say?
Like a year before?
Is Is that what you Is that what you
want me to do? You want me to say the
guy planted a tree?
Are you Is that what you want me to do?
Okay. Like 6 months before the tree
starts
out of the seed, you want me to call the
guy a tree planter?
You You're You have a problem. You can't
wait till the end of the process
to call the seed a tree seed, right?
What about What about the guy who
who brought who What about the guy who
picked the seed out of the apple last
year?
Is Okay.
Is it a tree seed then?
Okay. Is that guy a
a tree planter?
Okay, the indirect cause of the tree
that's not there yet.
Okay, direct cause I can see it. You
know, we can wait a week.
You can say something wrong for a week
until some leaves come out, you know. We
could call We could say the tree
grew. Okay, go water the
tree.
You know, that's okay, but what about
the guy who planted the tree seed, you
know? What about the tree planter?
You know, they say, right? They say go
plant trees today. Like in China, you
have like
holiday.
Nicholas likes this part.
He's so handsome. I'm going to get in
trouble.
Yeah, you can say, "Okay, got it. You're
all right."
Did you hear enough about this question?
Okay.
All right. So, Nagarjuna's conclusion is
it's not really acceptable
to talk about a thing growing
that isn't there yet.
There's something wrong.
That's a sign
that things aren't coming
from where we thought they're coming
from.
Maybe
the tree doesn't come from
the tree seed
which cannot be a tree seed anyway.
Got it?
Maybe
you plant
a little piece of carbon
and then
you know, couple of months later a stick
comes up and maybe they're not connected
at all.
And maybe they're both coming from you.
Got it?
Nagarjuna, okay, I understand. That's
really cute.
But what's the use of it, you know? Why
Why are you spending 2 weeks in Arizona?
You realize how you're going to talk to
your family when you go home?
What did you learn in Arizona? There's
no tree seeds.
What else did you learn? You can't plant
a tree.
Then they're like, "Oh, you're going to
go again?" "Oh, yeah."
Uh
The point is you can change the husband
yelling in the kitchen
without talking to him.
Okay, no direct contact between your
voice and your husband.
Okay, you can make your hus- if you're
smart
if you're a true follower of Nagarjuna
you can make your husband to wash the
dishes for the rest of your life
without discussing it.
Now all the women are like, "What? Say
that one again."
The men have to listen to her or else
you're going to be stuck washing dishes.
Got it? Easier way to get what you want.
Okay, easier way to to get happiness.
Okay? The idea
that talking to your husband will make
him stop calling you phantom
is mistaken.
Okay? And you can try it for the rest of
your life and it will just give you gray
hair
or no hair.
Okay?
Don't give give up this old system.
Use a new system. Oh, it's coming from
how I treat other people. Okay? I should
stop yelling at my kids. Okay, got it?
Stop coming to Geshe Michael and "Can I
Can you solve our problems
with this person?" You know.
Look at my shirt. It says
"Shut up and do the four steps."
Let me translate my book.
Okay?
All right, take a break. Pee-pee break.
We'll do questions when we get back.
Okay. You're first.
Okay. All right, pee-pee break. Uh juice
break.
Juice break.
By the way, I remind you that uh we're
going to have a
traditional
incomprehensible
Sojong ceremony afterwards if you'd like
to
watch it. It's all in Tibetan. You don't
understand anything. We don't either.
Quiet quiet and quietly.
Or tomorrow.
Or ming tian jian.
Huh?
Thank you.
Rest it tomorrow.
I'm afraid we cannot finish.
Yeah.
So, two things I promised you tomorrow.
The technical meditation information and
the
question. Okay?
Mean too.
Okay.
Mhm, homework question number four.
Nagarjuna is focusing on
the idea of a cause
at the beginning of the seed of the
sprout coming up, okay? We talked about
the process, the tree is growing, the
problem with the tree is growing, okay?
But, what's the problem with saying that
the sprout first came out of the cause,
okay? What's the problem there? And by
the way, I'm not reading you the verses,
but this is how the verses go.
Okay? And uh
when I have time, when people give me
time
to translate it, you can see the verses.
All right?
And I can do a nice job.
Okay.
Uh
what's the problem
at the beginning of the process when you
say the seed
kicked off the growing, the the seed
triggered the growing? Then, what's the
problem with that?
Uh
and I'm going to read you You okay?
Exactly. So, here we go.
I'm going to read you the answer. If you
can write fast enough, you
but I'm going to say it fast.
The eye of points out that if the result
were absent at the time of the seed
if the result
if the tree is not there
when the seed is planted, okay? If the
tree is not there
when the seed begins to do its thing,
then you could never call the seed a
cause.
Okay? If there's no tree,
there's no tree cause.
Okay? Cuz it didn't do anything yet.
Right now, it's just a piece of stuff.
Okay?
Uh
Yeah, boo boo.
He's going to have such cool seeds. You
got to bring him every guy that I
brought.
There's four more. This is number one.
Every fall.
Okay?
We need an airplane. That's all we need.
Okay.
Uh if the result were present at the
time of the scene, then the seed would
have nothing to do.
Okay?
If the tree is there
when the seed starts doing its thing,
then why should the seed do anything?
Let the seed retire.
Okay? Let the seed have a break. But,
if there's no tree when the seed starts
doing its thing,
well, how can you call it a cause?
There's no result.
Okay?
That one is not very fun.
I just put it in there cuz I needed a
couple of homework questions. Okay? But,
that is the next verse. That is the next
verse. That's an easy one.
I don't like easy ones.
Okay. Let's go to the next homework
question. Uh
Now, he's going to go and cancel each
one of the four kinds of causes one by
one. He's going to pick on them
one by one.
And I thought we would have some fun.
Okay?
So, maybe we don't finish the homework,
but that would be a pity.
But I'm going to read you something from
uh
word wordsmith text. Uh
Okay, he's one of our translator. He's a
member of our translator team.
He lives in Guadalajara, where all the
cool people live.
And uh
he's translating a a famous book by
Tsongkhapa
about the mind only school.
Tsongkhapa explains all the mind only
school, okay?
And
Ooh, I agree.
Okay.
Uh
because
when uh
Tony Lama explains Nagarjuna attacking
these four kinds of causes, okay?
And maybe we don't finish the homework
today, okay? Maybe we do some of it
tomorrow, okay? Sorry.
I don't know how we're going to manage
that.
They get it back and I don't know.
That's Tim will figure it out.
His hair is getting more and more like
this.
I'm just jealous.
Uh
So, when Tony Lama attacks the four
he doesn't say the four are wrong.
He says the definition
of the four is wrong, okay? The
definition of the four
is wrong, okay? So, this class, I'm just
hopelessly going deeper, okay?
And I know I will lose some of you
by next time we meet.
I'm okay with that.
But, I'll tell you if you can stay, if
you can come back next time, uh
it's deep, okay? If you want something
uh fluffy, come to DCI
number two
or something like that.
I can do that.
But, it's kind of frustrating for me. I
I would like to have a group of tough
people
who want to go deeper, okay? Because
my lama said, "When you go to the dollar
store,
take a hundred dollars."
It means
uh
when you go to teach a one-hour class,
have a hundred-hour classes in your
head, okay? All right? So,
I'm going deeper.
If some of you want to
go to the dollar store with a dollar,
that's okay. Okay.
So,
he attacks the definition. And he
doesn't have a chapter
that I know about yet
about definitions.
But, if it was me, I would have 28
chapters.
And I would put a chapter about
definition. So, I want to talk about
the definition of definition
and the emptiness of definition, okay?
Because he doesn't attack the four
causes.
He attacks their
definition, okay? And uh
I think it's significant. I think
there's a reason, okay? So, I think if
you understand a little bit more
about how we say a thing is a thing, how
we decide a thing is a thing,
then it's another emptiness. It's
another party chat, it's another
examination you can do. Okay? All right.
So, we're going to slide over
to the definition of definition. All
right?
Because he attacks their definition. And
in English, I don't know about Chinese
or Spanish or German.
But, we say, "He's an idiot by
definition."
You see what I mean? We say by
definition. It's Then, what's that mean
by definition? It means if you go look
up idiot in the dictionary,
what it says there fits this guy
perfectly. He's over there, right?
Fits perfect. Okay? Then, we say,
you know, nobody made him an idiot. He's
just an idiot
by his nature, by nature. Okay? So, we
have by nature, which we're going to
study tomorrow.
And we have by definition, which we're
going to study today. Okay? By
definition
in English means
if you go to the dictionary and you look
up what is idiot, you know, does stupid
thing,
then
it fits perfect.
Okay? Then, we can say by definition,
he's
idiot. Okay? All right.
I can only use these words until
tomorrow cuz my partner's coming and she
doesn't allow me to use these words.
So, I'm trying to use all of them today.
Uh
okay.
So, what's the And this is in Adam's
text. Adam is translating an
unbelievable text.
It's all the stuff you need to know for
emptiness. His book is called the key to
emptiness. Okay?
Uh
say tar ya.
tar ya
choo sum ta ma
choo sum ta
ta ki ya
choo sum ta ma
se nyi kyi chi nyi
definition of definition
definition
What is a definition?
What is a definition? It's anything
that has uh
I'm sorry.
Yeah. No.
J Say j ya.
J ya.
Chos sim tam. Sorry.
Senny katsenny.
Uh the definition of a definition
is that
three
substantial things, three real things,
three concrete things must be true.
Three concrete things
must be true, okay? Then it's a
definition, okay?
All right?
Then the definition of what you define
there's a definition
of what you define,
okay? There's a definition in Buddhism
of what you define. In English, in
logic, it's called definiendum.
The thing that you are defining, okay?
Like fire,
we can say it's the thing we want to
define, okay?
And then we can say hot and burning
is the definition of fire in Buddhism.
The element of fire is defined as uh
In Tibetan it's
s- sekpa. Yeah, sashing sekpa. Yeah,
like jinsek, right?
Fire offering. So,
the thing we're defining is
fire.
The thing we're
using it to define it
is uh
hot and the thing that thing which is
hot and burning. And in English you
usually put quotation marks around that.
I I don't know why.
Okay. Um
I'll tell you the three qualities
of a of a definition, okay?
But I'm more interested in the
substantial part.
Okay, what does that mean?
Because that
relates to the first chapter in the
Vajna, okay? You okay?
Stay with me. By the way, tomorrow we
reach the second chapter.
Which is cool. All right.
Uh,
Zaya Tsen Suma. So, definition of what's
of a definition. Let's go to that one
first.
Let me get here.
By the way, I'm using
Yeah, I'm what I'm using one of Tony
Lama's teachers.
Which is Jam Yang Shayba. Okay.
Okay, here's the three substantial
things
that have to be there
if a thing
is a definition. These are Here are the
three substantial things
that have to be there
if a thing is a definition. Number one,
generally, it should be phrased as a
definition. It should sound like a
definition, you know? Like, that thing
which is
Okay, in English you have to say, when
you define something, you have to say,
that thing which is hot and burning. So,
it should sound like a definition. So,
number one, it should be
a definition. In English, you have to
put quotation marks around it.
Okay.
That thing which is
hot and burning. So,
A, it should be
it should look like a definition, okay?
Number two,
uh,
you must be able to confirm it
in the thing you're defining.
You must be able to confirm that it's
there
in the thing you're defining. So, if hot
and burning
you choose it as the definition of fire,
then when you go stick your hand in the
thing called fire,
you should go ouch.
Okay? Then that confirms yeah yeah that
definition is for this thing.
Got it? That definition fits this thing.
This thing that burned me.
That definition is fits this thing. A,
it's a definition. Sounds like a
definition. B, it does fit this thing.
This thing burned me. I checked it. Is
it a good definition? Let's put my
finger in there. Ah, hmm, yeah. Good
definition. Okay, it fits. That's
quality number two. Third quality,
that definition shouldn't fit other
things.
That definition shouldn't fit other
things like water.
Okay? Like if you stick your finger in
water,
uh
it shouldn't burn you. You see what I
mean? Got it? It shouldn't fit other
things.
Okay?
All right. Generally,
I mean, there's probably some exceptions
we can come up with. Joe's already got
three, but
make a song and
Are you going to play this time?
I
We're we're hoping you get something
together.
Uh okay.
But what I want to talk about is the
zeyo part. Why does it have to be
substantial?
Now, here's where I have a problem. When
we were discussing it in the translator
course
couple weeks ago,
seems like a hundred years ago.
Uh
Okay, listen. It seems to me
that the words
hot and burning, in quotation marks,
right?
Uh
I would have I'm sorry.
It seems to me that the definition is
words.
And the thing is a
solid thing. You see?
Fire
is a is a real thing. You see what I
mean? To me, it feels like that.
And then the definition is just some
words in the dictionary.
You see what I mean? It feels like that
to me.
The definition
is words in a dictionary. It's It's not
going to burn your hand if you
touch the definition
on in the paper, you know? Hot and burn
Touch hot. Hmm? Nope. Burning? Nope. You
know? So, I always felt like
the definition
is more an idea.
You know? And then the thing is the
thing. It's fire, you know? It It It
does does things, okay? But
in Buddhism
the fire is the idea.
And the definition is the reality.
Hot
is hot.
Burning burns.
Fire's just a word.
So, it's reversed. It's the reverse.
It's the opposite. Okay, I want you to
struggle with that.
Okay? It's like causes and effects. I
think you should have had a chapter
called definitions.
An examination of definitions. But if
you think about it, in the definition
Buddhist definition of
definition
they say the definition's the real
thing.
And the other thing's just a word.
Fire's just a word.
Okay? Got it?
That the substantial thing is the hot
and the burning. Okay? That's the
definition.
Right? Yeah.
Then the other is just a word fire, you
know? You could call it
agnya agnya organ
or organ.
agwin
Yeah, panimayam.
uh pa- pajar
sap
What is a big fire what's a little fire?
Am I right?
in Russian
Agwin is a teach me.
pajarita
guro
major thing
Okay, anyway.
uh
Got it?
And the point is
uh
You ready?
It's the hot
and the burning
in the fire.
Okay. It's the hot
and the burning
in the fire.
All right. I I I didn't ask that.
It's the wet
and it's it's
and flowing in the water. uh
Which means, okay, get this. This is
where I'm going.
Is it possible to walk on water?
You see? Is it possible
to walk on the water?
If the definition of water is the thing
that goes to scoop and you fall down and
you know, if that's the definition of
water,
okay? Is it possible to walk on water?
And and I see these pujaris these
priests Hindu priests in India, they
will pick up a red hot steel.
I've seen it
and they they go like this.
You know, and everybody's like, "How you
do that?"
It's because the hot and the burning is
not in the fire by definition.
Or is it?
And the wet and the blub is not in the
water
by definition.
Got it?
So, where I'm going is
when the gajina attacks the four causes,
which he's about to do and that's why we
won't have time to finish them in the
class.
When the gajina attacks the four causes,
the way he says it is, "I'm attacking
their definition.
I'm attacking their definition."
Which to me means I'm attacking that
they could have cause causeness inside
of them.
They don't have causeness inside of
them. They're not causes by definition.
They are not causes. Being a cause is
not inside them.
Okay? It's coming from you.
If the pen can write a book, that's
coming from you. It's not in the pen.
The book is not in the pen.
Okay? The ability to write a book,
which is kind of the definition of pen,
maybe,
is not in the pen. The ability to write,
an instrument for writing,
is not in the pen. Okay?
Then again, you know, you're going to
say, "What's the use of that, Geshe la?
Why we have to know that? Why we pay to
come here from China, and you know, and
all that air fare?
Or Berlin or Munich, you know, to hear
that?"
I've keep telling you, if you want your
husband to wash the dishes
forever if you're from Ukraine or
Kazakhstan or
It's up to you. If you don't If you want
to wash the dishes, I don't mind.
You don't have to study in the kitchen.
Okay?
The weird thing is I enjoy washing
dishes.
And I'm the dishwasher in our family.
I was the dishwasher for 8 years in the
monastery.
Those are pots.
Three Three guys get on a ladder to get
in the pot.
And you wash it like this.
Cuz it has to feed 1,000 cups of tea,
right?
Okay. Anyway,
that's That's dishwasher.
Now, uh
Just briefly, the definition of the
thing to be defined,
which is fire,
is the three qualities of the thing
which is not
Nick, help me out. I forgot your Which
is not concrete.
Okay.
Okay. Opposite of concrete. Concrete is
the
definition. Fire. Sorry.
Hot and burning is something you can
touch. The word fire is not something
you can touch. Fire is a concept. All
things being defined are concepts. They
have no
big reality. They just have a small
reality.
That's terrible.
I should say it different.
They are not concrete, okay? They're not
substantial. That's what he said.
Okay? They are
exist nominally, okay?
In the fire
is a name.
Hot and burning, you can touch it, okay?
The definition is touchable.
The thing you're defining is not. Okay?
But
does the definition exist in the in the
fire?
That's the question. Or did you make it
hot?
Who made fire hot?
I did. Okay. Who's going to make your
husband wash the dishes?
I am. Same thing. Same question.
Okay? Second one is more useful.
Okay, got it? So ta ya chusum tsawa
is the definition
three qualities
of the thing which is not not
substantial, not concrete.
Is the definition what it conceptual's,
okay? Conceptual's great.
Three conceptual qualities
is the definition
of the thing we define. Like fire. Like
fire. Okay? Now, if you want to know the
three, number one
generally speaking
it's something we want to define.
Generally speaking, so it's just the
opposite of the other three.
It is something we want to define. Fire.
Okay? Generally speaking
it is something we want to define.
Number two,
it's def it fits its definition.
We're just going the other way. It fits
its definition.
Okay?
And it's
it's not something that any other
definition is going to define. It's not
something
which any other definition is going to
define. Now, this is not on your
homework.
Okay? I I wish I had put it on your
homework, but I thought of it today.
Uh so it's not on your homework. I'm so
sorry.
Uh
but it all came from that word in the
explanation.
Nagarjuna is attacking the definition
of the four. Okay? All right?
That's how he attacks the form.
Now, let's go back. We have
7 minutes. Maybe we can do one more
homework question.
Uh generally speaking,
it is something to be defined.
Okay.
Yeah.
Oh, it doesn't fit any other definition?
Okay.
That's nice.
Okay, I'm going to give you homework
question number five, and we won't get
to 6 7 8. So, I don't know how you're
going to deal with that, Tim.
Just give him 100 on the homework.
Just kidding. I repeat, those people who
have the most homeworks done
get certain perks
at Nagarjuna number two.
Like I think you should get We call the
Israeli Palace.
That's the nicest house in the whole
valley. It has two toilets.
And
right? Am I right?
Yeah. It's like uh
It's better than the Trump Tower.
Uh
better than the Ping An Building.
Okay. Anyway,
and you get extra points if you do all
of them. Okay, Tim? Like 20% extra.
So, you can get six points for five
homeworks. Got it?
Okay.
So, you're definitely going to beat
those people who didn't come to all
their classes.
All right.
But, they should still try because if I
have more than 110
next fall, I will choose the ones who
did their homework first, okay?
Who have the most points, and the other
ones just bye-bye.
You go to buoy and study Nagarjuna.
Okay.
All right.
Good luck.
Okay.
Causal condition is defined basically as
anything that has a result.
Okay, the first of the four
conditions
is defined
as anything that has a result. Okay?
Then Arya Nagarjuna says, "I don't like
it.
This definition has a problem, okay?
Anything that has a result." I don't
Anybody want to guess what he's going to
say? Guess what's the answer. The The
question is, "Why doesn't Nagarjuna like
the definition of the first cause
as anything which has a result?"
He doesn't Nick doesn't like in it.
Peter, what do you not like?
Okay, that's one opinion.
Wait.
Say it again. You're closer. You're
closer than these guys. You're not
Tibetan, yeah, but you're close.
Say again.
Yeah, good. You're very close. Now,
someone tied up with the verb for me.
Someone tied to the verb for me.
Anything
Anything she said the the result is a
future thing, okay? And she's very close
to the answer. The guardian that has a
problem with the word has.
The cause has a result.
Huh?
Yeah, don't exist yet.
It don't exist yet, you know?
I also have a big bank account, okay?
Understand?
Future.
I'm waiting for all my donations to
Diamond to come back.
They're so slow.
Got it? Okay.
The cause is donating to Diamond. The
result is, you know, I'm super rich guy,
you know? Understand? Have money?
Can I say I have money from my donations
to Diamond? Can I say? No, it's a future
thing. It didn't come yet.
Okay? All the people that I owe money,
you know.
Okay, right?
Okay, it's a future thing. You cannot
use the word have for a cause and a
result.
They cannot exist at the same time.
What, a result has a cause?
The cause is gone, man.
It was going while the result was coming
out. We just said that. That was
simultaneous time periods. When it
finally came out, the cause finally
died. In that moment one of them is
gone. How can you say you have something
if it doesn't exist yet? Okay, got it?
You all right?
When you use the word has, I have a
book, you have to exist and book has to
exist in the present moment. You cannot
say, "I have a book." If you're getting
the book next week.
Okay? It's not correct.
After you get the book, you can't say,
"I'm ordering a book.
I have an order in for a book." The
book's already there. The order's
finished.
Okay? Amazon took it off their thing,
except they're tracking everything you
do.
Okay? Got it?
You can't use the word
"have"
if one thing isn't there yet. Or if the
other thing stopped already.
Got it? The result can have a cause, and
a cause cannot have a result. There's a
problem with your English language.
There's a problem with all human
languages. They are mistaken. The
languages reflect the mistake of the
human mind. Okay? The word we, I and me,
is a mistake.
It's we.
Okay? I give Aldo
I give Aldo a bite of my I don't know.
Last night all I had was a strawberry.
I give Aldo
a bite of my strawberry.
But no, Aldo was giving me strawberry.
We were eating strawberries.
Right? When I put in his mouth, I put in
my mouth. Right?
If I give him strawberry, I get
strawberry.
Right?
So,
Aldo
McAldo McAldo
ate strawberries.
McAldo give McAldo
strawberry.
Okay? And McAldo get strawberry.
More.
Because McAldo happy, McAldo give McAldo
strawberry.
No, that's how God talks. That's why he
doesn't talk to you.
Okay.
I'm not kidding.
You won't understand it.
You'll say God is crazy.
All right. We finished homework question
five.
We did not finish
six.
And we did not Is there a seven?
Seven or eight? Oh my gosh. Okay.
So six, seven, eight we still have to
do.
So I mean Tim, I guess they just do
their homework anyway and
I'll I'll let you guys decide.
I think it's cruel to leave them with
nothing to do today.
You talk to Tim. He's the boss.
I'm I'm just a teacher. Okay.
Turn your mic on. You ready? Loud.
Pretend you're singing in Vietnam.
Shanti
Om
Shanti Om
Shanti